hey what look guys my name is a China
welcome back to my C++ series so today
we're gonna be talking all about costing
in C++ we really haven't talked about
this often although we have in fact used
costing and will talk more about kind of
say style costing as well as save us
lost out costing and this this video one
color absolutely everything we'll get
into this as a series kind of goes on
and I think that this topic is one of
those things that you just have to
practice with and kind of learn through
experience rather than me just telling
you this is how it works because if you
just take in the theory with no practice
for this specific topic it's not really
gonna help you that much so just keep
that in mind okay cool
so first of all what is casting well
what I'm talking about casting I'm
specifically talking about typecasting
or any kind of conversions that we have
to do within the type system that we
have available to us in C++ C++ being a
strongly typed language basically just
means that there is a type system and
types enforce if I make something as an
integer
I can't suddenly just start treating it
as if it was a double or a flirt or
something like that or vice versa I have
to kind of stick to my type unless
there's an easy implicit conversion
which means that this simple swaps knows
how to convert between the two types
with no data loss and basically what's
labeled as an implicit conversion as
well or there's an explicit conversion
which is where I'm actually telling
simple as hey you need to convert this
type into this type now we have covered
kind of casting and type conversions to
an extent when we talked about type
punting so if you haven't seen that
video definitely check that out
but in this video we're gonna kind of
formally cover what casting actually
means and see how we can use it so the
way that we perform type conversions is
visibly explicit type conversions is one
of two ways really or at least I see it
as one of two ways there's the kind of C
style costs and then we also have a C++
style costs now if we just take a look
at a quick example I just say I've
gotten the integer like this I'll call
it a and I'll set it equal to 5 and I
want to I want to treat it as a double
now in this scenario if I make a double
called value and set it equal to a you
can see that that we don't need to
explicitly specify hey I want you
a into a double because that's that's a
that's kind of a conversion that it
deems as implicit it's easy to do
there's no data loss anything like that
now if I had something the other way
around where I had maybe double value
equals like five point three five point
two five or something like that and I
wanted to convert it into a integer that
would also be deemed as an implicit
conversion because it's not something
that we necessarily have to specify hey
I'm converting this type into this type
now if we did want to be explicit for
example what we can actually do is just
cast this double into into an integer by
doing something like this right now of
course in this case it implicitly is
able to do that but for the sake of this
let's and since we are talking about
cost and let's pretend it wasn't so we
have an implicit we have an explicit
conversion here because we're saying I
want this value to be competitive to an
integer now why we need this is kind of
it's not really perhaps a better example
might be like if we wanted to maybe have
another double here called a and we
wanted to add you know five point three
to this value now if we just kind of get
rid of this and print what a actually is
then what you might see it's obviously
what you might expect with kind of
adding five point two five to five point
three now if I cost this value into an
integer then that's going to converted
into an integer which means it's going
to truncate at the point two five and
I'll end up just being five plus five
point three which instead of giving us
ten point five five would give us the
value ten point three submit in this
case is actually changing it and this
actual technique that we've used is
called a safe style cost because we
basically specified the type that were
causing to in parentheses like this and
then the variable that we're actually
costing optionally we can of course
surrounded in parentheses like this
which is particularly useful if maybe we
wanted to cost that entire thing into an
int once it had actually evaluated in
fact if we do this will still get 10 as
the value because value is gonna be five
point two five plus five point three
which gives us ten point five five and
then it would get truncated into an ant
now the C++ way of doing this would be
by using as a both
starcast and it'll be four days who
would use something called a static cast
and to do that basically this would look
like the following so let me just get
back to where we were before which is
just this and then it's been this would
just be a static cost what we're passing
into which is it needs and then the
value and then we'd add 5.3 and that
would be our value now C++ tile costs we
have a number of them one of them is
called static cost we have something
else called reinterpret cost we have
something called dynamic cost and we
have something something called const
cost there's a kind of the four main
costs now what you have to realize is
that they do not do anything that C
style casts cannot do what I mean by
that is that sure they might do
additional things but the actual
conversion the result of what you get is
a successful type conversion c-style
cast can achieve all of that so this
isn't really adding new functionality
what it is adding is kind of like syntax
sugar to your code now of course dynamic
cast which we'll talk about specifically
in another video I'll show you an
example of it working here but we'll
talk more in depth about what it
actually does and how it works in
another video that for example will
actually perform a check and may return
null if the conversion wasn't successful
so it does do extra things which also
means that it actually kind of slows you
down but for the for the most part all
of these hippos boss style casts don't
do anything really extra they just kind
of are a way to put into English words
static cast for example that it's a
static cast and they also do some other
compile time checks in the case of
static cast to see if that conversions
actually at all ever possible and
reinterpret cast as well is kind of
putting into words the whole type Pawnee
thing that we talked about it's just a
way to put it into words like
reinterpret cast I'm reinterpreting this
memory as something else Const cast I'm
removing cost I'm adding Const the
benefit to having all these costs apart
from those kind of compile time checks
that you might receive is you can now
search for them in your code base all
right if I want to see where I wear my
casting is maybe I having performance
shoes and I want to not dynamic cast
something I can search for dynamic cast
I can search for static cast if you just
have a cast like sa self.cards like int
or whatever like we did with that
previous example how you're going to
search for that you can't really search
for it's not something that you can of
course you could use like a regex or
something like that and actually just I
don't know it just it wouldn't actually
be practical to do that whereas here
we've got actual English words that are
very easy to search for so it just helps
us both as a programmer reading our code
and writing our code but also it helps
us to reduce kind of errors that we
might accidentally make if we try and
cast certain things that are
incompatible good example is we've got a
few classes here banks derived in
another class if I just try and cost
this value which is clearly an int into
like I don't know another class that's
going to result in an error because well
it came in this case it's going to be
because of a constructor but if I add
like a pointer or something like that
now to this case you can see it's an
invalid type conversion so what simple
class has done is the compiler has
looked at that and been like that's
never gonna work right and even if we do
take the memory address of it right
which of course gives us an inner
pointer and we try and type on it that's
not gonna work it's invalid type
conversion now for type owning as I just
explained we would need to use
reinterpret cast and if we do you can
see we don't get any errors who've now
reinterpreted the data that is at that
value pointer into being a pointer to
another class instance but the point is
with with things like this it adds
actual compile time checking because it
knows that we can't do certain
conversions whereas this wouldn't be the
case of course if we just used a normal
say star cast it were just kind of
default to doing what a range Shepherd
cast would do and I'm saying a lot of
words and it might be a little bit hard
to follow but again the best way to to
actually learn this stuff is just a
practice it try and build yourself an
example of using static cast or
interpret cast a Const cast a dynamic
cast I'll show you a dynamic car
cast example any minute but just trying
to get yourself and then that's the best
way to kind of work out how it actually
works and when you can use each one so
if we take a look at dynamic cast what
dynamic class will actually do is
suppose that we had maybe we made a
derived class instance right so I said
derived derived equals new derived and
then somewhere along the line I decided
to actually cast that into a base right
so a base base equals derived now what I
want to do later is figure out ok hey I
have a base pointer is it actually a
derived instance or is it in another
classes since we can say they both
extend base now if I try and use it what
I can do with dynamic cast is actually
kind of not only asked that question but
attempt that conversion and do something
if it fails so we know for a fact based
on this code that base is actually an
instance of the derived class but let's
pretend that we didn't know that and
we'll just say another class AC equals
dynamic cast another class and then AC
right and one pointer and of course ok
now what's gonna happen here is if we
had just used a static cast which by the
way we can see we can do in this case it
does the same thing as a safe star cast
or if we use this a star cast it would
just work like isn't it would just give
us that value and of course things might
go wrong later on because you know AC is
not in fact another class it's actually
a derived instance we've just basically
type ones it but with dynamic cast what
it's actually going to do is it's going
to see if that is actually the case and
of course over here I need to make sure
I pass in base and not AC let's hit that
five and see what happens so you can see
once I actually do that if I hit f10 AC
is equal to null because it is in fact
not bad and of course you could then
check it you could say if not AC or if
IC equals null then maybe we know that
it's not that class or a way to check
for if it is that class is just to say
if AC that means that the type of
conversion was successful and we now
know
bass is in fact an instance and instance
of derived right sorry an instance of
another class and of course if I do
change this around so it works by
setting it equal to derived hit at five
and then you can see if I hit up ten
here it does in fact you also valid
pointer because that conversion was
successful so dynamic cast is a great
way to see if it's actually worked now
this does tie in very closely to the
runtime type information RT TI and it
requires requires a whole bunch of
things which we'll talk about in a
specific video about dynamic casting but
just so you know these casting operators
are kind of available to you as a way to
simplify casting and to maybe make it
more solid in the sense that it will do
compile time checking dynamic cast will
do runtime checking and you'll get all
that kind of hopefully more solid code
base by using casting operators like
that me personally I tend to use C style
casts most of the time but I do
encourage if you're working on a brand
new project that you're starting from
scratch or if you have a very small
project you should use sea salt say
sorry C++ start casting like static cast
dynamic re interpret cast all of that
kind of stuff because those those casts
do make your code more solid and are
better for everyone involved really and
cons car didn't really touch on but
that's just literally you use it to add
or remove Const to something easy you
can add constantly anyway but it's
mostly for removing Const and again it's
good to just have that in your code base
because now you can search for all the
naughty times you've decided to remove
Const and maybe fix that or just come up
with something else as well
so that's really useful and then the
other thing was reinterpret cost if you
look at that type hunting video that
I've linked at the beginning of this
video everything I did there you can
basically use very Tober cost so that
kind of that's what reinterpret cast is
used for it's when I don't actually want
to convert anything I just want to take
that kind of pointer and interpret it
something else I want to interpret
existing memory as another type that's
what our interpret caste is useful
anyway I hope you guys enjoyed this
video if you didn't hear that like
button you can help support this series
by going to patreon accomplice after the
turn okay showed out to everyone who
supports this series because it would
not be here without you guys and it
certainly wouldn't be wouldn't be an
ongoing thing that I keep keep doing so
yeah thank you because I love making
videos for you guys I will see you next
time good bye
[Music]